So today we're going to continue in our discussion of dynamic programming.
I actually found this set of problem session problems to be easier than the previous one.
I think there's a funny thing, which is we learned in class
about sort of pseudo-polynomial time style dynamic programs.
Somehow that language is a little bit liberating in the sense that you're sort of using parameters
that you really shouldn't when it comes to the runtime of your algorithm.
Well, I suppose you should in the sense that it's allowed
if you call your algorithm pseudo-polynomial time.
But somehow it makes it a little easier to formulate your dynamic
programming algorithm because sort of all the numbers are staring you.
Right in the face. You don't have to be so careful
about what's fair game and what's not when you pose your
algorithm so long as it's efficient in the values that you care about.
And so today's problem session has five problems squeezed in instead of the usual four.
We'll see how far we get, seeing that I usually talk too much anyway.
But I'll try to stay on schedule here, and we'll see how well we do.
Any questions from our students about dynamic programming before
we get started here? We can cut one if you want. We can cut one?
Oh, I will gladly cut one if I run out of time. Yeah. OK. So without further
ado, let's get started with coin crafting, which is problem 9-1 here.
So I suppose it should be keel-naffery if I were
to work through my spoonerism properly here.
In any event, we have a thief who's in desperate need of money, as with
many thieves or else, of course, they wouldn't resort to the world of money.
So we're going to do that. We're going to do a little bit
of crime. And keel-naffery here has n identical coins.
I've been very self-conscious about the way that I write the letter
I ever since Eric pointed it out. And it's only gotten worse.
Now it's inconsistent and hard to read. But in any event, so we have n
identical coins. And of course, these coins have very distinctive markings.
So we can't possibly run away with them as is because if you take them to your standard
jeweler, they'll immediately recognize that these
markings are bad and stolen and that's not so good.
So instead, we can melt these coins into other objects.
So our sneaky thief here has identified a potential buyer.
And the buyer has a few criteria here. So we have a buyer. And then
we have a thief. And then we have a thief. And then we have a thief.
And then we have a thief. And the buyer has a very strange
value system, seeing that apparently it's easy to take coins
and make them into other things. But in any event, the buyer,
what they care about is not the fact that the coins are made
of gold, but rather that they like particular
objects better than others made out of said gold.
So in particular, they have a different rate for each object, like a
different price they're willing to pay. And so they have a list of...
N objects that they're interested in. And each
one is associated with two things, n objects.
They have a price, so the amount that the buyer is willing to pay for
that object, which again is not just the weight in gold for some reason.
There's a value added tax in this universe. And then they have
a price. And then they have a price. And then they have a price.
And then they have a price. It takes a
different number of coins to manufacture.
So maybe I can make a golden chocolate fountain and
that takes 10 coins. But I don't want two of those.
So if I make that, then the next thing I have to do
is a figurine of Eric and Jason to put alongside it.
And having more than one of those would also be creepy
and weird. So I can only make one of each object.
And of course, my goal here is I have n coins. By the way, the fact that
there's n coins is a good thing. It's a good thing. It's a good thing.
It's a good thing. It's a good thing. It's a good thing. It's a good
thing. But I'm going to have n coins and n objects for the buyer.
It doesn't really matter. I mean, it will for the runtime. But you
could imagine this being n and m. So I wouldn't be too hung up on that.
And what you're trying to do is, of course, maximize your
revenue subject to the constraints that you have n coins.
And you can't make two objects that are the same. Hopefully,
you've captured the essence of our problem. OK, fabulous.
So as with all of our algorithms, we've dynamic programming
problems in 6.006, we have a paradigm for how to approach
them which has a cute acronym which is sort bot and I think sort bot is a
totally relevant and straightforward approach to this problem here. Yeah so in
particular let's give ourselves a bit of notation right so we're gonna number our
objects between 1 and n just for convenience so we'll say that p i is the
price of object i okay and we'll say that k i is the what the problem calls
the melting number in other words if I want to make object i this is the amount
of coins that I'd have to melt to to make that object okay so just a tiny bit
of notation and in general so okay what do
we do when we formulate our dynamic program?
We want to identify interesting sub problems we could solve that are smaller and when we
compose them all together we get the final solution to our problem and
this particular problem involving manufacturing objects out of coins I
think is like a really classic one when it comes to dynamic programming this is
the sort of thing where you know someday when you're trying to pay for your
tuition by doing these like hacker contests online you know like this is
the sort of thing that comes up all the time
in that universe right Erm So in particular,
the to sort of variables here you know when I make a new object is what object
did I make and how many coins did I spend when I did that sort of the two
natural parameters to use when I solve by dynamic programming problem yeah and
and of course is going to be sort of recursive in the sense that I can either
choose to make object I or not and it doesn't matter what order I'm making
my objects in or similarly what order I spend my coins in which is usually
nice property to have in dynamic programming universe. So
in particular, oh, this thing is my nemesis. This is front.
I think this classroom is particularly tough for short people
because it's like I'm moving it up and down all the time. OK.
So given our observation here, if we're doing sort bot, so what's our S
again? Let me ask myself that. Subproblems. Thank you, Professor Domain.
Then essentially, what we want to do, based on what I sort of
argued verbally, is maybe define our variable xij, the thing we're
going to compute, to be the revenue
from using i coins and objects 1 to j.
OK. So in other words, I have i coins left in the
bank, and I'm only allowed to use the first j objects.
And we can already see that this is kind of a sensible way
to approach this dynamic programming problem in the sense
that there's an obvious recursion here. I choose to make an object. I have
fewer coins. And I can sort of imagine there being a topological order
in the sense that I could first decide about object 1, and then object 2,
and object 3, and so on, or vice versa, depending on whether you're a. OK.
Prefix or suffix kind of guy, which I still get backward.
But the good news is that it doesn't really matter.
What matters is formulating the equation. OK. Any questions about our
definition of the thing that we're going to chase after here? Fabulous. Ah.
OK. Right. So let's do a let's continue sorting. So our next piece
of our puzzle here is the R. I believe R stands for recursion.
This is a new acronym for me, too. Oh, nope. Relate. But it
might as well be recursion for most of these problems. Right.
So the basic relationship here is that, of course,
I can either use object j or I can not use object j.
And in both of those cases, if j is the very last guy that I'm going
to consider, that'll be a totally reasonable, recursive rule. Right.
So in particular, I have that xij essentially can take one
of two values. So parentheses, in case you're wondering.
And of course, you're trying to maximize your revenue. So let's do that.
OK. So we have sort of two potential options, but we have to be a bit
careful. Is there a case
where I can't make object j?
Yes, class, there is, which is the case where I don't have enough coins
left in the bank. So I want to make that really expensive fountain,
but I only have one coin. Then I'm sort of out of luck. Yeah. So let's
do these two cases. So first, if a oops, I got my cases backward.
That's OK. Right. So let's say that I choose not to make object
j. OK. So what does that mean? So did I spend any coins? No.
And moreover, what is my maximum profit? Well, it's
going to be the same as the maximum profit using
objects 1 through j minus 1, because I didn't use
object j. Yeah. So in particular, that would be x.
Let's see. I got it backward in my notes, so we're going to do it live,
like that. OK. And otherwise, let's say that I did choose to make object j.
Well, what happened? So I did get some revenue now.
So I got, man, what on earth did I write on these?
So I get the price of object j here as my revenue, but I spent some coins
in the process. So I have i minus case of i, which is the number of coins.
What was that? Case of j. Oh, thank you. Sorry. Case of j. That's why we
should be consistent with our indices when we write these things down.
So I spent case of j coins making this thing, object j. And
moreover, I can still choose to make any of the previous objects.
So it's still just j minus 1. But I have to be careful, because I can't
always do this. In particular, this had better be a positive number, or at
least a non-negative number. Because if I end up with a negative number
of coins, well, that's not a physical universe that I choose to be in.
So in particular, what we need in some sense is i
minus k minus j, kj to be greater or equal to 0.
Or equivalently, i is greater than or equal to case of j. I think you
guys could all do that one at home. OK. And this is our recursion.
Hopefully, I've gotten it right, because it disagrees with the crazy thing
I wrote in my notes at 1 AM yesterday. OK. Bye. Bye. Bye. Bye. Bye. Bye.
Bye. It's great.
Awesome. Well, so I think this is pretty straightforward. Essentially,
either I can choose to use the last object, or I choose not to.
And either one of those, of course, decrements j, because that's the
index of the object I'm considering. And I either account for the price,
but have to pay in gold. Or I don't account for the price, so implicitly
there's a 0. And I don't have to pay in gold. are kind of similar.
But for now, we'll do one or two carefully. So T, I believe,
stands for topological order. And here, it's staring us in the face
because notice that xij only depends
on x question mark comma j minus 1.
So of course, on your problem set, you should write things
more carefully. But the basic point here is that there's
a clear topological order just by looking at that second index because if
you think of all of your x's as variables in a graph, which we've actually
drawn in lecture. So maybe these are all the i's. And then the j, so i
goes down and j goes to the right. Then essentially, this argument is
saying that all the arrows kind of point left in this graph. So I
suppose the way I've drawn my arrows, this isn't quite accurate.
But it actually doesn't matter. The only thing
that matters is that it goes from right to left.
But I'm going to erase this so that you don't remember it. OK. So in
general, just when you want to make your topological order argument,
I think a totally sensible one is like looking at the indices of your
recursion and then just trying to find some number that decreases.
Incidentally, if you take a differential equation course, that's
roughly. How you prove that a lot of those things converge too.
So there's a sort of a generic math trick that we use a lot. Do
you call that in ODE where you have some number that decreases?
I would call that potential function. Potential function, that's a
perfectly sensible one. It's not Lipschitz. It's some other mathematician.
Anyway, OK. So let's continue sort bot. So next, we need b, which
is our base case. So in this case, it's pretty straightforward.
If I don't have any coins, I can't make any money. I have a t-shirt
that says that at home. And moreover, if I can't sell anything,
I can't make any money. So those are pretty straightforward
cases. So we have that 0 equals x of 0 comma j.
Remember, the first index is the number of coins you have. So
this is saying I can't make anything. I don't have any coins.
And similarly, equals x i comma 0 for all i, 0. i, j.
So this is the coins and the objects. OK. So let's see.
I keep writing these problem sessions too big and then spending
half of it erasing. So let's try and fit this on one board here.
So we're going to do sort bot. Then the second, no, the first O because
there's no O in sort, is the original problem that you want to solve.
So of course, you start out with n objects and n coins.
So the original problem we want to solve is equivalent to computing
xn comma n. And then finally, we've got to do our runtime.
t stands for runtime, or time, I suppose. So first of all, how many
subproblems are there? Well, there's xij. Both i can go from 0 to n.
This is a great way to be off by 1. So there's n plus 1 squared subproblems.
And how much work does each subproblem do? Well, it does boring work.
It's just a formula. So there's order 1 work per
subproblem. So the overall algorithm takes n squared time.
So I promised to do something in our last problem session that I didn't do.
I didn't actually do it. So I did think I would spend just a minute here
translating what this sort bot thing would mean in terms of
code. Because I think that it's a little bit implicit here.
In particular, I think this step here, I mean, you will see
that it really clearly is going to give you an algorithm.
But I think it's kind of easy to, again, just to forget what your code
actually looks like. And actually, the coding problems on these problem
sessions are almost too interesting and can obscure it
a little bit. So I thought we'd do a boring problem. Ha!
And show you that it's really not so hard to do this.
And in fact, we covered two different strategies in class
for how to take sort bot and convert it into a piece
of code, although they might have kind of zipped
past you in this 2x speed thing that you can do now. So right.
So here are two options. One of them is called memoization.
And the other, I don't know, bottom up, I guess, is a reasonable
phrase to describe. And so I thought we'd do them both,
because they're both easy for this particular problem. So let's do
that. Ha! OK. So let's do that. So is this necessary on your homework?
Strictly speaking, no. Like, if you've gone through sort
bot, then essentially everything that happens after that
is sort of boilerplate in terms of converting these steps into a
piece of code or an algorithm. But I do think just for understanding
why sort bot makes sense, it's worth thinking about for a
minute. So option A here is memoization. Ha! Memoization.
Ironically, I've taught MTA algorithms a few times,
and I never actually knew what memoization meant.
So I learned something from Eric's lecture the other
day, which remember, memoization, the key thing,
and then what apparently is kind of a made up word is memo.
Like, if you're back in the day, and you had a Steno pad,
and you were writing down stuff because that's
where you solve problems with your slide rule, then,
essentially, the idea is that if I compute xij for some ij pair, I
shouldn't compute it again. I should just write it down on my memo pad.
Stenoization sounds better to me, but I suppose we'd have to go
back to the 1940s and fix it. OK, so let's actually write down.
I'm going to write down pseudocode that'll probably
look more like MATLAB because I'm that kind of guy.
So let's say that I wanted to make
a function, which I guess is revenue.
So ij like that.
And this is the thing I wanted to compute. That's actually going
to be a problem because I'm not going to be able to see. OK, right.
So in addition to this, I'm going to kind of pass in
an array x, which is going to be like my memo pad.
This is going to be terrible coding practice, but easy board
coding practice. So if I were in C++, maybe I pass it by reference
so that when I edit, it's a treble clef, but whatever.
When I edit x, it actually persists when I recurse. This
is terrible coding practice, and you shouldn't do it.
OK, but it's just going to be because I don't
want to write too many lines on the board here.
And maybe we initialize, like we have some helper function to,
let's see, we want our revenue to be big, well, actually no.
We'll just initialize it to not a number so that we know that we
haven't computed it yet. How about that? OK, so what should we do?
Well, if we're going to memoize, the first thing we should
do any time that I call my revenue function on an AJ pair
is check if I already computed it. So in my kind of goofy, bad board coding
style here, what could I do? I'd say, well, if I've already computed it,
then this thing won't equal nana anymore. It won't be not a number. So
I can say, OK. If xij does not equal not a number, so in other words,
it is a number, return.
And this, I think that this little line of code here, it gets a
little lost. But this is like, we should put sparkles around it.
This is the magic of dynamic programming because I just killed
recursive calls. Right? Like, even if i and j are like 17 and 12,
I'm going to be able to do this. OK. So I'm going to do this. So
I'm going to do this. If I already computed it, I'm done. Right?
I don't have to call my recursion again.
OK. And otherwise, what am I going to do?
Well, otherwise, I'll maybe call. Do I want to write
it all down? I don't want to write it all down.
So otherwise, I'm going to evaluate r, where r is this formula
over here. Notice that this will require recursive calls. Right?
And I'm going to store it in xij and then return xij.
OK. So basically, the only difference between what we've seen in
the first 2 thirds of 6.006 and now is this beautiful line of code.
So if I already computed this thing, return it.
And this is the memoized version of our algorithm.
I think this is the easiest one to maybe think about. But
actually, from a runtime analysis, it's a little bit annoying.
It's not in the sense that we convinced ourselves that sort bot
is OK. But of course, if you're thinking about your recursion
tree, what's happening is that you're sort of maybe convincing
yourself that this piece can be lopped off in your function calls.
So you have to do your counting carefully. And there's a different
way to implement the same thing. So this would be option b.
This is maybe more efficient, maybe less efficient, depending on
your problem. But these are all within constant factors of each other
for the most part. Not always, but for the most part. This would
be bottom up. And this is the idea of rather than just taking
our recursive algorithm that we already know and then just checking
a table to say, OK, did I already do this? In that case, return it.
In the bottom. Up version, I'm going to build up my array xij.
So there's no recursion at all. So what would that look like?
In the bottom up case, notice that in some sense the memorization
is a top down strategy. I would call it on n comma n.
Here, we're going to start from 0 and work our way toward
n. So we'll start with x0j equals xi0 equals 0 for all ij.
Obviously, I can do this with a for loop. And now, well, remember, if
we think about our topological order, xij only depends on previous j's.
So it makes sense to have an outer loop, which is over j.
And now, inside of this outer loop, I can compute anything
that I want in that j column of x. And I'm in good shape.
Because I'm building it up one column at a time. So in
particular, now we can do our loop over i, and then just have xj.
And now, evaluate our r step in our sort bot paradigm. And notice that
that's perfectly fine. Because by the time I get to computing xij,
I've already filled in xij minus 1, which is all I needed to evaluate
that formula. So what are the advantages? And the disadvantages here?
So notice that here, our runtime is staring you in the face.
We have n squared subproblems, order 1 work, and you're done.
On the other hand, there's some possibility. Like if you were an
old school AI person, that you might be able to do some pruning
on your left hand side that I can't do over here. So
here, I'm literally evaluating every entry of xij.
It could be the case, it's not the case for this particular
problem, but maybe xij only depends on xij minus 5.
This strategy is going to still build up that whole table. This one
maybe can skip over some entries. So in practice, it could help.
On the other hand, here, I've got a bunch of recursive calls
I've put on the stack of my computer that here, I don't have.
So I think actually, because of the overhead of recursion,
typically, the strategy on the right is preferred, also for clarity.
But that's a blanket statement that I shouldn't make. OK, so
anyway, I think I've done this problem. I've done it to death.
Are there any questions here? I just thought I'd fill in for
something I promised last time and didn't actually do. OK, fabulous.
So we'll go on to problem 9.2. So this is continuing
from last time in the saga of Tim the Beaver here.
So I forget what Tim the Beaver was doing in our last problem
session, but today, Tim the Beaver is going to the career fair.
And as we all know, the. The only real purpose of
going to a career fair is to pick up free stuff.
We joke, actually, you guys should all go to the career fair. I got my
first job out of college by going to a career fair and haranguing somebody
that picks our booth until they let me in. But in any
event, so Tim the Beaver is not interested in getting a job,
but rather just wants swag, just wants free stuff out of booths at the
career fair. So in this particular problem, there's n booths. Is it booths?
It's certainly not boots. I don't know. There are n booths, each of which
has swag. And in particular, each swag has a value associated to it,
which is ci, which is the coolness of object i. It
additionally has dun. W-i, this is the weight of object i.
And just to make this problem verbally difficult
to communicate, there's a W-a-i-t associated
with each object, which is the time it takes to wait in line and pick up
object i. And Tim the Beaver, if there's some ridiculously cool object
with a low wait time, he might just keep getting in line and getting
more of that object. So unlike Kiel-Nafri on our first problem,
Tim the Beaver is perfectly happy to
have more than one of the same thing. OK.
In addition to this, just to make this problem, in my opinion, slightly
more annoying and point losing, Tim the Beaver also takes one minute
to get in line at any booth. So we're just going to have
to remember that when we account for our time, ti. OK.
OK. So let's continue adding some more constants to our problem. So
each booth has an object which has coolness ci, weight wi, time ti.
Tim is carrying a bag. The bag can hold a particular
weight b. So this is the max weight that Tim can hold.
And one of those weights is the amount of time that Tim can hold
in his bag at any given time. And finally, Tim is a greedy beaver,
but he also can go home or go back to his dam, I suppose, and empty his
bag. And so h is the amount of time to go home, and back, and empty his bag.
Right? empty his bag in the meantime. And again, just to be
annoying, don't forget, he encouraged plus 1 to get in the next line.
This is what made my answer wrong, and I'm bitter, so I'm going to
keep complaining about it. So of course, what he wants is the max.
It's sort of a, what would economists call this? I don't
know. But for Tim the Beaver, he wants the max total coolness,
or MTC, which is, of course, a number that we're all trying to
optimize in k minutes. You might remember those old TV shows
where you get like one minute in a grocery store to empty the shelves into
your cart kind of thing. So he wants to do this, and the computation time
that he's reserved for this is order n b k. And it was a big setup. I
tried to document all the different constants that are in this problem.
I don't think I missed any. OK, fabulous. So incidentally,
continuing on k, k is the total amount of time that Tim the Beaver
has allotted to do his job fair scavenging. Fabulous. Right. Any other?
Cool. OK. Notice that this is going to be an example of a problem
that was sort of not kosher in last week's problem session in the sense
that k is included in our runtime. But what is k? It's just a number.
k doesn't scale on the size of your problem in a linear way.
So it's not going to matter for how we solve our problem,
but it is just a feature that's worth pointing out. OK, so how do we
solve dynamic programming problems? We use a sort bot or a senior BST,
if you are watching previous iterations of this course. OK,
so let's do that. See, I'm trying to conserve board space.
This is not going to end up succeeding. So again, what are all the
different subproblems here? Well, somehow, what are the different things
that are limiting Tim the Beaver? What are his constraints? Well, he only
has so much time. And somehow, this is going to sound more philosophical
than I intend, but time always moves forward. Right? For Tim the
Beaver. So it's a pretty good candidate in terms of dynamic programming
because there's not going to be some cyclical
dependency. Remember that in dynamic programming,
we're all about trying to identify topological orderings
in our subproblems. And when you see something like time,
not only does it also begin with t, but it's useful in the sense that
time moves forward. There's never a case where Tim the Beaver purchases
like a weird warp speed airplane and somehow goes back in
time. That doesn't happen in this particular homework problem.
And for Tim the Beaver's sake, I hope in no homework problems.
So this is a long-winded way of saying that time is a pretty reasonable
constraint to put in our problem. Not constraint as much as index, I guess.
Moreover, there's another thing which is limiting Tim the Beaver,
which is the capacity of his bag. Remember, he can only hold weight b.
But this one should give you the heebie-jeebies a little bit. Because
this problem as a twist has allowed the bag to empty itself out.
So it's not true that somehow you can come up with subproblems where
Tim the Beaver is just monotonically decreasing the weight of his bag.
However, if he does choose to decrease the weight of his bag, he has to
spend time doing it. So time continues to move forward for Tim the Beaver.
And that's what's going to give us our topological order.
Yeah? OK. This is a little too philosophical, I guess.
But in some sense, this is a long-winded way of saying for our sort-but
paradigm here, a totally reasonable thing to do would be to have xij.
I don't think in this class we do this definition notation.
xij equals the max coolness where he has i, minus, i minus.
So if I have xij in i minutes and he has j weight, let me glance at
my answer to see if it's left in his bag or weight that he's carrying.
Left in his bag. Either one would make a reasonable problem. I'm just
bad at looking at my notes and seeing the disagree with the board.
So I'm going to try and stay consistent. OK. So xij is the
MTC. But in i minutes with j weight left rather than in. OK.
So I'm going to try and do k minutes with b weight, which is going to
be our base problem. OK. Oh, no. I did it out of order. Disregard that.
We'll get to the
b in a minute. OK.
OK. So that's our subproblems.
So now let's do the R in sort-but.
OK. So let's say that Tim the Beaver has i minutes left in the clock, and
he has j weight in his bag. He's got a number of actions that he can take.
Yeah? And let's think about what all those actions are. By
the way, there's one thing that plausibly Tim the Beaver
could do, but he doesn't really need to, is do nothing.
He could do now, but then in 10 seconds do something.
You could account for that in this problem, but there's sort
of not a reason. He might as well stack up all of his actions
and then leave all of his leftover time at the end. You can convince
yourself that that's sort of OK. Tim prefers a compressed schedule. Right.
So he's got a lot of energy, this beaver. That's what they
say. Nature's construction workers or something. OK. Right.
So let's think about all of our. So for one, Tim the Beaver could
not do a damn thing. He could just sit around for the rest of time,
and that would be perfectly fine. So a different way of putting that is
that he could give up. How much coolness would Tim get from giving up? Zero.
That's right, kids. Giving up makes you zero cool. So OK. Right. So Tim
the Beaver is trying to maximize. He has a lot of different options.
One of them is zero. Meaning he gave up. Right. Notice he could
recurse like x. I guess what would be he could give up for one minute
and have that be x i minus 1j or something. Forget if I'm going to do i
plus 1 or i minus 1j. There's no reason. He can just give up and stop.
That would just be extra recursive cost for no good reason. OK. The
next thing that he could do is he could get in line for a booth. Right.
So first, let's work out what happens then. So for one,
he gets coolness. Let's say that he gets into booth k.
So he gets coolness ck when he does that. And now he can recurse. So
first, we have to account for the time. So it takes tk. That's a t.
Time or does it? No, because it takes an extra minute for him to get
in the next line or to get in this line, I guess. This is better.
And moreover, he needs to account for j minus wk, like that. Can
he always do this? No. He needs to have this much time remaining,
and he needs this much time in his bag, or this much weight
remaining in his bag. You guys can work out the inequality.
But since I only have a foot here, I'll just say if, applicable.
OK. OK. This is a great way to lose points on your homework.
But for board writing, it's OK. So when I say applicable, I mean
these two numbers had better be greater than or equal to 0. OK.
And you can do this for all k. So in other words, he can choose to get
into booth k. And Tim has the third option, which is he can go home. OK.
So what happens if he goes home? Does he cool when he, does Tim
the beaver get cooler when he goes home? No. I'm afraid to say. OK.
So in particular, but he does spend time. Yeah. So how much time
does he spend? H. What was that? Maybe he should have lost coolness.
He should have lost coolness by going home. No, home is cool, guys,
especially this semester. Stay home. Stay indoors. So he, right.
So he loses home time, h, and 1 to get in the next line. OK. But he's got
a devil's bargain of sorts. He loses time, but he gains bag, bagginess.
Weight is the word that I'm looking for. B, like that. OK. Again, in
this case, remember that he still needs if i is greater than h. Right.
Otherwise, he's in trouble. By the way, I wrote this in kind of an
annoying way. There's a different way of saying that is i minus h minus 1
is greater than or equal to 0. OK. OK. But I'm going
to stay with that. I'm going to stay with the answer,
because I'm going to be able to do the whole thing
without any of this. And so the answer here is 0.
Which is really what's applicable in our recursive call. But this is a
strict greater than sign. There was another little thing that caught me up
when I was reading the answer here. OK. And those are all the
options for 10 the beaver. Yeah? Notice that every one of our options
either gives up completely or decreases time. So
we have our topological order, which is again,
Again, on your homework, you should write out your answers. What is our
base case for Tim? Well, how much coolness do you get if you have no time?
0 coolness. That's how much. So we have this expression, x0j
equals 0 for all j. Incidentally, although it's perfectly fine
to have this be your base case, you're actually, in some sense, didn't
need it because Tim the beaver always had the option of giving up.
So you could, I guess, in this problem have no base case if you really
wanted. Would be OK, but kind of weird. OK. And what's our original problem?
Well, he starts out with time k and weight capacity b in his bag.
So it's xkb. And then finally, we need to do our runtime analysis.
So how many subproblems are there? Well, again, a subproblem is basically
just the number of indexes for most of our dynamic programming problems.
So the first index is time. The second one is bag size. This
is always between 0 and b. This is always between 0 and k.
So there's order kb subproblems.
How much time does each subproblem take? Well, notice that I have to loop.
So I'm going to use over all of my different options k here. So I incur.
Oh, I'm noticing k is abused in our answer to this problem. We
should use k only once. OK. So here's where I made a mistake.
And I believe it's in the written solution, but I'm not going to
check now. There's k, which is the total time that Tim the beaver has.
And there's the k that I use as an index here. And those are not the
same. So I'm going to use k bar really fast. There you go. Problem solved.
And I just noticed that because I was doing my runtime. And it's not
order k. It's the loop over all the k bars. How many k bars are there?
Well, these are all the different booths. And there's
order n of those. So this is order n time per subproblem,
which gives me a total runtime of order kbn.
Which I believe, uh-oh, our desired runtime was order nbk. But I think
we can convince ourselves that indeed, those are the same thing. OK.
So my apologies for a slight overloaded character
here. But honestly, it's kind of one of those things
if you read the answer, you probably wouldn't even
notice. But now that I'm saying it out loud, I am. OK.
And that solves Tim the beaver's maximization problem. He's a very
cool beaver. Any questions about this one? Notice that both of these.
problems are very similar in nature. I basically just wrote subproblems
indexed by every possible thing and then enumerated every possible solution.
I think this is totally sensible. Like, again, I remember I had
a math professor in college that always would use this phrase.
It's important not to think here. And I think this is
absolutely true for these dynamic programming problems.
Somehow they look a lot more complicated than they are.
Fabulous. So problem three, protein parsing. Ah, yeah.
So this one also got me tripped up for a minute because the
runtime they want is not the runtime of the obvious solution,
but it kind of sort of is after a little bit of fixing. OK. So Professor
Larrick Ander has a laboratory. And that laboratory processes DNA.
OK. So let me go to my notes here because I think they're easier
to read. Right. So I'm going to go to my notes here. OK. Right.
So a strand of DNA, as we all know because we're MIT students, is equal
to basically a strand of characters that are like A, C, T, and G. If you
asked me to name what those stood for, I could make a stab at one
or two of them. But I'm a failure of a, like, I did not have the GIR
because I went to Stanford. And this is why I'm apparently a poorly educated
person, according to a person in a faculty meeting. But in any event.
OK. Right. So we have a strand of DNA. It's basically a
long string of characters that are one of four options.
I'm told that there's sometimes like a fifth and a sixth
option, but not too often. This problem there's not.
And moreover, so a strand can be cut up. So I have this
big, long strand. And I'm looking for certain markers.
In particular, I have a list, p of markers, which are really, like, the
most common ones. And I'm looking for a sequence of less than or equal to k
nucleotides.
By the way, this really is something that people do. Like, string
searching really is applicable to processing these DNA strands.
Obviously, I think in practice, these techniques
have to be a lot more resilient to error.
But really, a lot of these algorithms we're covering are not
all that far off. Data sets, which is pretty cool, I think. OK.
So what are we going to do? Well, we have a
string. And then we're going to make a division.
So we'll call our string s and our division d, which kind of looks like
d1 to dm, which are substrings that concatenate to make the full guy. OK.
So if s is our input string, then a division d is just like chopping up s
into little substrings, each of which we can give a name, little d here.
So big D is the full division. Little d is all the little pieces.
There's that old song about going through the big D in Domi in Dallas.
I think it's for divorce. I don't know. Um. Right. Right.
So OK. So the value of a division is the number of strands.
So strands are these little d's here that are in our list p. OK.
And so right. So given s and p, what we want is the max value.
And the runtime that we're budgeted is kind of a weird runtime. And this
should make us a little suspicious. So the max value is big O of, I think,
I wrote it slightly differently in the problem, but whatever. I
distributed a k like that. So it's k mod p plus k squared mod s.
So we have two terms here, which somehow smells funny in
dynamic programming. OK. OK. OK. So what are we to do?
Well, what I did is I ignored our desired runtime, came up with a dynamic
program, and noticed that it was a little wrong, and then fixed it.
By wrong, I mean it was correct. It just wasn't
fast enough. OK. So let's do version one here.
1.0. That makes it more accurate. They're more precise. Right.
I always confuse those two. So here's a sort of thing that is
going to be a little bit funny because it's going to look
like we're going to have an easy computational problem.
But then it's going to turn out that it's actually too slow.
So in particular, in our s in sort bot, what we could do
is say xi is going to be the max value of a suffix. If
you're wondering, I don't know the difference between
a suffix, but I wrote the word suffix in my notes and checked it at
home. Si comma colon. See, it's suffix because it starts at i and it goes
to the end. Huh? No comma. In MATLAB, it would be a
comma. And that's a colon, and that's an i. OK. Thanks.
I'm inventing my own programming language on the board as we go today.
All right. So and notice this is kind of a reasonable set of sub-programs.
Right? Because kind of obviously, if I lop off some piece of my string,
then the max value I can get is just the value of whatever remains. Yeah.
So spiritually, this somehow feels like the right
dynamic programming. And indeed, we'll see that it is.
But it just requires a little bit of lipstick at the end to
run on the right time. OK. So let's do our recursive call.
And this is actually straightforward.
At least the sort of recursive call that you want to make is
straightforward. And then we'll see that there's an equivalent formula, which
is the one you'll see in the solution, which looks more complicated,
but it is the same thing. So I'm going to write it as pseudocode
for our recursive call rather than as one giant formula
because I think it's easier to follow. Not pseudocode.
I know that's frowned upon in this class. A description of a set
of steps for obtaining our recursive call rather than a formula.
So in particular, we're going
to initialize. X i to be 0.
We want to do a maximization problem, so initializing a variable
to 0 is a sensible thing to do. And remember, what can we do here?
So we're looking at a suffix. I could go down my list, p, of all
the different markers, see if any of them matches the first couple
of characters of my string. If it does, I get some value,
and then I hop on to the next thing. That make sense?
Oops, I'm realizing I have a slight mistake here. Rather than initializing
to 0, I actually have one additional option that I forgot to account for.
I could just not use this character. I could put it
in its own little snippet and get no value from it.
So maybe initially I make a recursive call like that. It would
be OK to initialize it to 0 and then do this, but whatever.
Notice we're already seeing the t in our sort bot. Start to kind
of stick out at us. We're going to only depend on bigger indices i.
But in addition to this, this isn't enough. This would
obviously just recurse the end of our list and do nothing.
We get value if we can find a substring that's in our
list. So what we could do is for each marker in p,
remember p is the list of things that we're looking for.
What could I do? If the marker matches s starting at
i, I'm going to just not even attempt to do Python,
starting at i and ending at the length of the marker, well, what could
I do? I could get $1 by matching. You know. Matching that object.
And then I have to hop forward the
length of the string in my recursive call.
Well, I could do that or I could not do that. And I want to
maximize. So I could keep my old value or I could get 1 point
by using this as my match plus xi plus the length of the marker.
OK. OK. And this is actually, in my mind, the simplest
possible dynamic program you could come up with.
This is actually a totally fine dynamic program.
We'll just see that the runtime isn't good enough.
OK. So does everybody agree this is a way I could solve this
problem and it would give me a correct answer? I'll do the t bot.
Yeah, that's what we're going to do. But we're going to maybe skip some
parts of sort bot. OK. So in particular, what's the topological order?
Notice that I always look to the right when I make a recursive call.
What's my base case? Well, in this case, it's just x of 0, I guess,
because I'm looking forward. Oh, I'm sorry. My base case is x of
the whole length of the string, which is going to return 0, right?
Because if I have no string, I can't get any value out of it.
The original is x of 0, meaning that I want the whole string.
And let's actually do the runtime. OK. So I'm going
to do the runtime analysis, as Jason suggests,
because that's, of course, the relevant computation here.
So this is t 2, because it's the second t in sort bot. OK.
So how many subproblems are there? Well, I mean, it almost looks
like we should have a fast algorithm, because our subproblems are
only indexed by i, right? So there's one subproblem for basically
each character in the string. So there's mod s subproblems total.
But how much time does it take for each subproblem? Well, let's
be careful. So there's a for loop over all the markers in p.
So I know that I incur at least mod p work in my subproblem.
Is that all the work that I incur? It kind of looks like it.
Because there's only one for loop, and there's an if. But how do I check if
strings are equal? Well, I have to iterate over the length of the string.
So I incur a second cost, which is checking if two strings are equal. We
know that our strings are at most, well, I didn't actually write it down.
But the problem tells us that our strings are at most length k.
So I incur another factor of k in every one of my subproblems.
And that implies that our whole algorithm that I've outlined for
y'all above takes, mod sk squared. Oh, I'm sorry. That was a lie.
If I actually multiply these things together, what I get, need more
sleep, spk. And that is against the rules. That's frowny face. Yeah.
Because in particular, I took two big numbers in some sense and
multiplied them together. And that's no good. So what is a person to do?
I tried to solve my problem. I came up with, by the way, from a partial
credit perspective, I think you'd be doing OK if you got to this point.
OK, not great, but OK. But of course, the problem is asking you
to solve this in this funny runtime, which is kp plus k squared s.
When I see a sum like this, remember that there are two problems to solve.
There are two strategies for solving problems in the algorithms class.
There's one which is useful in your everyday lives, which is to devise
algorithms. There's a second, which is to psychologically diagnose
your instructors. And I think that second strategy is actually pretty
effective here. I see two terms. Most of our dynamic programming things
involve filling in a table where you would expect there to be
a product. So in general, I would squint at this and think,
hmm, maybe I have to do some pre-computation. Yeah. In particular, we got
to do a lot of string matching in our problem. And maybe we can make that.
Yeah. That more efficient. Yeah, that's sort of the main question
here. Right, so this thing is too slow, and we're trying to fix it.
The way I'm going to try and fix it is to say, OK, well, I have
mod s subproblems. If I look at these two terms, how much work
can I actually do in my subproblem? Something that looks like k squared,
maybe plus this amount of pre-computation. See what I did there?
OK, so let's do that. So in particular. Here are
the types of queries that I'm going to have to make.
There's a bunch of times in my code when here's a number that yikes,
falling apart. That's what I get for sprinting across campus to get here.
I'm going to define a number, m i j. And it's going to be 1 if the
substring s i, oh man, 2j, is in my list of markers p and 0 otherwise.
By the way, why is this enough? Notice that I'm not
answering which marker. But the problem doesn't really care.
This problem is just checking if there is a marker, and if
so, then I use it. Yeah. So if I have this thing, that's going
to somehow make this for loop a heck of a lot easier, because now I
don't have to do string matching. We'll return to that in a minute. OK.
So my question is, how can I compute this thing? And by the way, notice
that I know how to compute this when the difference between i and j
is bigger than k, because I know that all of my markers have
length k or less. That's going to be important, because even
though m is doubly indexed, I don't actually need to do that.
In fact, I could even store it using less memory than that
if I wanted to by just storing that diagonal block. OK. All right. So the
other thing, which I think we saw in a previous problem session as well,
is that when we do a lot of string matching, it often pays to put our
strings into a hash table so that they're easier to look up later.
Does this string exist in this thing or not, rather than matching
every character every single time? So maybe we do that just for fun.
And in general, when you see a string matching
problem, I might, and you have a list of strings,
I'd suggest thinking about hash tables, just for fun. Yeah. Very fun
and profit. Yeah. So in step one here, maybe I put all the strings in p
into a hash.
OK. How much time does that take? Well, I have to process every string,
find its code, which is going to take order k time. There's mod p of them.
So this is k mod p time. Notice that that conveniently agrees with
our first term here. So we feel like, aha! We're in good shape.
We're making progress here. And now, maybe I want to fill in this m ij
object here. How could I do that? Well, for one, I'm certainly going
to have to iterate over all possible i's. Yeah,
so let's do that. So we're going to do two.
By the way, I'm using 1's and 2's and a's and b's and whatever.
These are just ways to denote steps of things. OK. So let's do that.
So let's do that. So let's do that. So let's do that. So let's do that.
So let's say that I just want to fill in m using a brain-dead algorithm.
So I could go from 1 to the size of my strings
for i. Careful. Now, I can't incur an s squared.
But I know that my strings are always at most length
k. So I could do for j equals i plus 1, 2, i plus k.
So this for loop actually incurs k time, not mod s time. And now,
I can do two things. I can find the hash of the string from i to j.
This is going to take order k time. And I can search
for it. Ah. No. No. No. No. No. No. No. No. No. No.
To see if it's actually in our hash table of p. And if it
is, then I set m equal to 1. Otherwise, I set m equal to 0.
Right. And these are sort of constant time operations, at least in
expectation. So how much cost to it? And so this, you can convince yourself,
fills in that array m. How much time does it take? Well, I have a
loop to the size of m. To the size of s. I have a loop of size k.
I have a second loop of size k here to compute the hash. So this
whole thing is going to take order k squared mod s time like that.
Notice conveniently, there's chalk on the floor. And this is the
second term in our runtime. So this is kosher. We can fill in m.
And that's a convenient object to have around. So
the only thing that remains is to revise our m.
And we can revise our r from above to make use of the
m that we have. And that's pretty straightforward.
So the trick is to not lean against this thing and to actually hit the
stop button. I'm learning. So now, I suppose we had t2 for the second t.
So for our revised r, we should have r prime.
What was that? The derivative. That's right. The derivative. Yeah,
we could do like Christoffel symbols, like i, j, prime, semicolon, k.
Take 6, 8, 3, 8 if you want to learn what Christoffel symbols are. Right,
so now, what is my recursive call for xi? Well, I want to maximize.
Well, what can I do? I can check every possible
length of a string. That could be in p.
Check if it is using my array m and get that amount of profit. So in
particular, I get m. By the way, I keep using the word profit here.
I'm essentially using that to mean increment in every single one of
our problems here. I like to think of our problems as maximizing profit
because I'm a greedy professor. So this is mij, which would
be like 1 if I found a string there and 0 if I'm not, plus x.
So I'm going to use i plus j to account for the length here,
where j is in 1 to, well, either the length of the string
or I get to the end of either the maximum length of a string in p or I get
to the end of my array, like that. OK, and this is our new recursive call.
The one thing we should double check is what is the runtime for
actually filling in x now? Well, there's still mod s subproblems.
And now how long does it take? Well, now I just
have one loop over k things. This is mod s times k.
It's actually less than any of the terms that's in our runtime.
And so this is fine. This actually is kind of a funny example
where the dynamic programming part of our algorithm, once we've done
all this cute pre-computation, is actually insignificant compared
to all the pre-computation that we had to do in our final
runtime. Sneaky. All right, any questions about protein folding
or whatever it is that we just did? OK, so as usual, I'm talking too
much. Can you cut one of these? Yeah, which one would you prefer to cut?
I have very few preferences.
OK, so one of the problems, I would take a vote. But with our
audience, there's a high probability of a split jury here.
Right, so there's two remaining problems. So I'm going
to go ahead and do a little bit of a problem session.
As usual, your instructor, you can leave it there. This is another
problem to learn about. Right, as usual, I've talked too much
and haven't gotten to the end. I get the impression that in
6.006, this egg drop thing is a bit of a tradition anyway.
So maybe we'll cover that problem really fast. Do they do
that in section, some variation? Not this time. Even better.
OK, so yeah, so maybe we'll do this egg drop thing, mostly, because the
other one, I think, takes a lot of verbal setup. OK. So maybe we'll do this.
The other one is, I would say, from a dynamic programming perspective,
maybe not super exciting, but from an interesting problem perspective,
it's kind of cool to think about. So I'd encourage you
to leave it in there. And you guys can read it at home.
From a coding perspective, it's also kind of fun. I noticed the solution
didn't do what I would do, which would be to use the bits in the,
you know, assume that something wasn't too tall and use the bits in
an integer to store your binary variables. OK. But that's an old hack.
It's sort of like this old hack for computing the square root
of a number that's apparently in the code for the Doom video
game, which involves bit shifting. And it happens to agree with
square root for some magic reason that numerical analysts really hate.
OK, so let's do lazy egg drop instead. So that's problem
four. OK. So we're in a building. Our building has n.
Floors and k eggs.
I guess it's debatable whether the building has eggs or
the residents. But in any event, I have some set of eggs.
And maybe I'm in the Stata Center or some other weird
building. So I don't have heights of floors that are isotropic.
But rather, each floor has a
different height, which could vary.
So it's height of floor.
Or I really want to write flower, but I digress. And we're going to
assume that our list is already sorted. So in other words, the fifth floor
is taller than the fourth floor. And we don't have to spend n
log n time doing that. OK. Right, so apparently in our problem,
we have an egg with a mysterious mechanical
property that we are trying to recover.
And we're going to have an egg with a mysterious mechanical
property that we are trying to recover. OK. So that's a good idea.
And then we're going to have an egg with n log n. OK. And all eggs,
as we know, are identical. So the only difference between eggs
is like chicken versus goose versus struggling to think
of a third category of poultry. Turkey, thank you.
Right, but assuming that I got all of my eggs at the same stop
and shop and they all come from the same species, then they
have roughly the same mechanical properties. Actually, probably the better
setup is that floors are very far apart relative to the size of an egg.
And if I get high enough, my egg, when I drop them on the ground
like that, breaks. Didn't break, but it could have broken.
And of course, if I drop it from an even higher height, my egg still
is going to break. However, if I have a very low floor, apparently
a very low floor, maybe this is a house for mice,
when I drop my egg, it actually stays intact.
And the question, as all good scientists want to know, is
what is the highest? What is the highest floor in my building
from which I can drop an egg and have it remain intact? And the question is
kind of a funny one. It's sort of like experimental design in some sense.
It's not asking, what is that, you know, like given this and
a list of experiments, try and infer something about the eggs.
But rather it's saying, if I carefully design a sequence of
floors. To drop. From. From which upon I dropped my eggs, then
what is the maximum number of experiments I need to do to triangulate
in on that floor, that critical floor above which my eggs break? Yeah.
So what I'm given are the heights of the floors and a budget of eggs.
In some sense, the budget of eggs sort of doesn't matter more than just
like putting a cap on the size of our problem in some sense.
What really matters is I'd like to use fewer than k eggs
to determine that because, of course, the remaining ones I'm going
to use to make an omelet. But notice that I can be a little sneaky
in my experimental design. That like, what happens if I drop my egg
from a really low floor in my building? Well, it remains intact.
So I can schlep down the stairs, I can pick up my egg, and I can
use it for my next experiment. And I have not paid an egg. Yeah.
So the first question you might ask is like, well,
why the heck wouldn't I just start on the first floor,
drop the egg if it's not broken, go on to the next one, and then
drop the egg and so on? That would be the most egg efficient plan.
And indeed, that is the case because you'll only break at most one
egg. But you're schlepping up and down the stairs a bunch of times
when you solve that, right? Every single time you've got to go retrieve
that unbroken egg, you've got to run down the stairs, pick the thing up,
and then run up to the next floor. And maybe in your optimization
problem, rather than trying to minimize the number of eggs
that you break, you're trying to minimize the expense on your
quads. And so instead, you skipped your leg day or whatever.
And the thing that you're trying to minimize is the sum
over the heights of the drops in your experiments. Right?
So you're trying to determine the mechanical
property of your egg by designing an experiment,
like sort of a procedure, that minimizes the number of times
that you need to drop eggs. Because every time you do, you've
got to run all the way back down the stairs and go look at the
pavement and see if the egg broke or not. That's a lot of work. OK.
This is different from the sort of classic egg drop 6006 problem, which I
encourage you guys to go seek out in previous iterations of this course.
Let me see. So right. And so the question is, what is the minimum number
of egg drops you need to do to ascertain that for any type of egg?
Yeah, so I give you a mystery basket of eggs, and you have to design the
experimental procedure and bound the number of this particular value here,
given a budget of k eggs. OK. And the amount of time that we have to do that
is order n cubed, kx. OK. Apparently, our building, we have lots of eggs
and not very many floors. OK. Does our setup make some sense
here? We're just trying to avoid running up and down the stairs.
That's the main takeaway. OK. So what are we going to
do? Sort bot, because that's all we know how to do.
And in particular, we're going to make one observation, which is
kind of handy. If I drop a floor, ooh, if I drop an egg from a floor,
I'm going to drop an egg. In this deterministic universe where egg mechanics
are very predictable, there's only one of two things that can happen.
Either egg broke or it didn't. Or I run into the board again. So let's
think about our experiment. Remember, at the end of the day, we're
trying to figure out the tallest floor in my building that I can safely,
from which I can safely drop an egg. So if I think about kind of bracketing
that height of that floor. Notice that I can always, for one thing, do I
ever need a bracket that's not a continuous or a connected set of numbers?
The answer is no. It should never be the case
that I think that my eggs could be on floors once,
only the prime numbered floors in my building or something. That really
makes no sense. Because if I convince myself my egg breaks at floor 5,
then obviously floors 6 through n, my egg also breaks in. So
I always can kind of just keep narrowing down some interval.
Right? So in particular, here's kind of a clever S in my sort bot, which
is to say that I'm going to say that x i j e is equal to the minimum.
By the way, I'm writing this as minimum total height. So this is like
the minimum total times I got to run down the stairs and check my eggs.
Or total height that I run down the stairs. The number of stairs I run
down. Assuming my stairs are one foot tall. Where I have e eggs left.
Notice the way that we've written the problem this time, I might
as well use all of my k eggs. Like that doesn't cost me anything.
What it costs me is running up and down the stairs.
And that I have floors i through j inclusive to check.
So in other words, if I'm on a floor below floor i, I've convinced
myself my egg won't break. Then if I'm on a floor above floor j,
I'm convinced my egg will break. OK? So what do I do? Well,
remember that this is sort of an experimental design problem.
I can drop my egg from any floor f, which is in the range i, .
To j. And of course, there's never a reason for me to drop an egg
from a floor below i or above j because we already know what
happens in that case. OK? So what happens when we do that?
Well, if I drop it from floor f, I have to pay in terms of my cost function.
Because I have to pay the height of f, I got to run down the stairs. OK?
But in exchange for that.
I learned a little bit about my egg problem. Right? I either get an
upper or a lower bound of f, depending whether the egg broke. OK?
So let's formalize that mathematically.
So in particular, we have x i j e.
Well, what do I get to control in my life? And what do I
have to deal with? What I have to deal with is the fact
that I don't know what's going to happen to the egg. It might
break. It might not. Right? And the egg might be an adversarial egg.
It wants you to run up and down the stairs. And I have to account for that.
But I am the egg's adversary and get to choose what floor I drop it from.
So remember, we saw an example, I forget what, from class, where there was
a game. One guy was trying to minimize. The other was trying to maximize.
In some sense, the egg is trying to maximize the amount of work you
have to do running up and down the stairs to do your experiment.
A better way to put it. Is that we're trying to upper bound the amount of
work in your experimental procedure. And I'm trying to design a procedure
that minimizes my work. So let's say that I'm the player. So I want to
minimize. And the decision that I get to make, the control that I have,
is what? Well, it's what floor I choose. So let's say I choose
floor F. Well, I have to go down the stairs, so that takes me HF.
This one's going up the stairs is probably what incurs the HF and
going down. It's nothing. But I digress. But now, I still am not done.
I've narrowed down into one of two cases. Either
F is my new lower bound or my new upper bound.
And I have to account for both of those in my recursion. And I have to
take the max of those two in the sense that I need in every possible case
that my egg drop experiment narrows down my floor to a width
of 0. So in particular, this is actually a minimax problem.
There's a max inside of a min here. So either the egg broke in my
experiment or it didn't. So if it did broke, then, well, what happened?
Well, let's see here. If the egg broke, then I got an upper
bound for my floor. So my lower bound remains the same.
It's I. My upper bound is F minus 1 because it broke on floor F.
Well, what happens to eggs when they break? I can't drop them.
I can't drop them from
floors again. So I lost an egg.
So this is my egg broke. OK. Or my egg didn't break. So in
that case, if my egg didn't break, now I have a lower bound.
So I'm only unclear about floors F plus 1. But the upper bound didn't
change. It's still J. And how many eggs? And how many eggs do I have?
Well, my egg didn't break. So I can run down the stairs, which is going to
be tiring. I've accounted for that here. But at least I can reuse my egg.
So I didn't lose anything. OK. And I get to choose. So
notice, oops. So do you guys see why there's a max here?
Essentially, I have to account for every possible
scenario when I'm designing my experimental procedure.
But I get to minimize in the sense that I can choose what floor. at every
step. So in particular, my F here is in the range i to J, like that. OK.
And now we have a recursive formula for our egg drop that minimizes
total height. So now let's finish off sort bot in four minutes.
It's actually not too hard. So I think we'll actually make it
for once by removing 20% of the problems I was supposed to cover.
All right.
So first of all, what's our topological order?
This one seems kind of annoying because, I think, usually, we think
of spending stuff in a lot of these dynamic programming programs.
So do we actually spend an egg? Not necessarily, right, because
in this recursive call, it'll bring exactly 8. Why spawn an egg?
Why is that even around? OK. You know. the number of eggs I
had remained the same. So maybe that's not actually a great way
to establish a topological order. But instead, what do we
know? What is, in science, the purpose of an experiment?
It's to improve our understanding of the world. In this case,
our world consists only of eggs and floors of buildings.
And in particular, once I dropped that egg, I learned something about my
building. And I narrowed down the range of floors that are uncertain for me.
So in particular, I know that x i j e only depends
on x, I guess, i prime j prime e prime with what?
Well, my subproblems, I always have a smaller range of floors
than I did before. So in particular, j prime minus i prime
is going to be smaller, strictly. Then j minus
i. And that'll give me my topological order.
Cool. And so that's actually, I think, the sort of annoying
part, other than working out this minimax expression here.
The remaining things are not so hard. So what are our base cases? Well,
let's say I have zero eggs left, but I still have a set of uncertain floors.
That's bad news. Yeah? So yeah. So that should be infinity. And
the reason is, of course, I'm going to take the min here, right?
And so obviously, I should never choose infinity as a min. So
in other words, I should never choose an option for a floor
that could possibly lead me to an uncertain scenario when I run out
of eggs. Yeah? In addition to that, there's another base case here.
So this is like I've got no eggs left, but some floors to check.
There's a second one. There's a third one. There's a fourth one.
There's a fifth one. I minus 1e. So in this case, I've got e eggs
left, and I'm done, right? I've narrowed it down to the bounds.
Incidentally, the way I wrote it in terms of inclusive versus exclusive
might be a little fishy. Over here, you guys shouldn't be off by 1
like your instructor often is. But in any event, here,
you're 0, right? There's no more floors left to check.
You've narrowed it down to a range of 1. Again, something
that I'm out of time so I'm not going to check carefully
is if my bounds are inclusive, should that be ij minus 1, ii minus 1, or
just ii? But I think you guys are all smart enough to work that out at home.
What should my original case be? Well, now I have all the
floors to check and all my eggs in my metaphorical basket here.
So I have floors 1, 2, and here. And the problem tells me I have k
eggs when I start. And then finally, I need to do my subproblems here.
I think you can actually simplify the argument that's written
down a tiny bit. And just again, look at your subproblems.
They're indexed by three numbers. I'm going to do a really conservative
estimate. I think the problem actually works out a better estimate,
but then asymptotically, it's the same. What's our bound on the first
and second index? Well, they're both just the index of floors. OK.
Which go between 0 and n. Yeah. Obviously, you could do better
than that, because the lower floor is always less than the upper
floor, which is what the problem accounts for. But if I'm being lazy,
then well, there's n squared subproblems to account for the two floors.
And the third index is your eggs, which you have m
of k of. OK. How much work do we have per subproblem?
Well, let's see here. There's a for loop over f. f is over
floors. Again, if I'm going to be really conservative,
well, there's at most n floors total in my building. And so that leads us
to a runtime of n cubed k, which is what we wanted at the end of the day.
There should be a big O here, because I think
technically, this is n plus 1 to account for floor 0.
So I'm going to be able to get a little bit more of a OK. And that
solves our egg drop experiment. Again, I think this is a nice one.
And I think in my mind, actually, in terms of
dynamic programming, this is one of the harder things
to get right, which are these sort of minimax games. You could
probably, I'd have to think about it, which in my negative two minutes,
I'm not going to have time to do. I think in
lecture, the way that we solved minimax problem, was,
I mean, we thought of there being two dynamic programming
problems that were sort of interacting with each other.
You could probably write this one in that form as well, I guess, just by
kind of pulling this term out and thinking of it as a different array.
But this form is perfectly fine, too. Either one's all
right. But in my mind, these are sort of the hardest things
to get right in dynamic programming. So I would choose whichever one
jives in your brain. So in your thing, should we choose to leave it alone?
There is a fifth problem here, which as usual, I haven't managed to.
OK. Get to, where you're kind of building walls by placing tiles.
This is an interesting one because your runtime is
exponential. But the problem tells you that that's allowed.
But there's some exponential things which are OK and
some that are not. Like essentially, what you don't want
is this product of two giant exponentials. You'd like to just
get it down to one. Basically saying it's going to be polynomial
if you have a small height of your wall. That's right. Or it's
polynomial in everything except for the things it's exponential in.
And moreover, the things it's exponential in are small. And the problem
says that. So I encourage you guys to take a look because it really
does take some time to logic through it. But the setup for that problem
is, I think, longer than my glacially slow board writing can handle.
But with that, we'll call it for the day.